<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Antheologia or The speech of flowers.</title>
            <author>Fuller, Thomas, 1608-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85008</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2409</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1647_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209092</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867994</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867994</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170210</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85008)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170210)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 207:E1647[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Antheologia or The speech of flowers.</title>
                  <author>Fuller, Thomas, 1608-1661.</author>
                  <author>Stafford, John, bookseller in London,</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 90 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Stafford, and are to be sold at his house, at the George at Fleet-bridge.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Lonon, [sic] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Fuller. Dedication signed: J.S. [i.e. John Stafford?].</note>
                  <note>With engraved frontispiece representing a garden.</note>
                  <note>A discussion in the form of a dialogue between flowers with some reference to events in Turkish occupied Greece.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Greece, Modern --  History --  1453-1821 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170210:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANTHEOLOGIA</hi> OR The Speech of FLOWERS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Stafford,</hi> and are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſold at his Houſe, at the <hi>George</hi> at <hi>Fleet-bridge.</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:170210:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of garden</figDesc>
                  <head>Anthologia. or The Speach of Flowers. Partly morall, Partly misticall.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sould by Iohn Stafford neare Fleete bridge.</hi> 1655</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170210:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170210:3"/>
            <head>To my much Honored Friend, <hi>William Stafford</hi> Eſquire, Merchant of <hi>Briſtoll.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this plundering age, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the fludies of ſo many have beene ranſacked, and many papers intended for private ſolace and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have bin expoſed to publike view, it was my fortune to light on the enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: It ſeemed to me pitty that it ſhould be strangled in obſcurity, as conceiving it might conduce ſomething to the delight of the Reader; for ſurely no ingenuous perſon can be ſo conſtantly ſerious, ye a ſurly and Criticall, but to allow ſome intervalls of refreſhment not onely as lawfull but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170210:4"/>
            <p>Let ſuch moroſe, yea miſchievous ſpirits pine themſelves to walking Anatomies, who brand all refection of the mind by ludicrous intermiſſions to be unlawfull, to ſpare an heavier cenſure (which may more reſent of anger) the worſt I wiſh them is alwaies to eate their meate without ſauce, and let them try whether their palate will be pleaſed with the guſt thereof.</p>
            <p>In the following diſcourſe there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing preſented but ſweet Flowers and herbs: I could wiſh it had been in the ſummer time, when the heate of the Sunne might have improved their fragrancie to the greatest advantage and rendred them more acceptable to the ſmell of the Reader: Being now ſadly ſenſible that Autumne the Vſher of winter will abate of their ſweetneſſe, and preſent them much to their loſs.</p>
            <p>Sure I am no bitter Colloquintida ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth this our Herball; I meane no tart and toothed reflections on any. Dull are thoſe witts which cannot make ſome
<pb facs="tcp:170210:4"/> ſmile, except they make others cry, having no way to work a delight and complacency in the Reader, ſave onely by gaſhing, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and abuſing the credits of others.</p>
            <p>It is deſired, that this diſcourſe may but finde as much candidneſſe as it brings, and be entertained according to his own inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency. I have heard a ſtorie of an envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, who had no other way to be reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of his Neighbour, who abounded with store of Bee-hives, then by poyſoning all the Flowers in his owne Garden wherein his Neighbours Bees tooke their conſtant repaſt, which infection cauſed a generall mortality in all the winged cattell of his Neighbour.</p>
            <p>I hope none have ſo ſpleneticke a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne againſt this my harmeleſſe Treatiſe, as to invenome my flowers with peſtilent and unintended interpretations, as if any thing more then flowers were meant in the flowers, or as if they had ſo deepe a root under ground, that men muſt mine to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand ſome concealed and profound my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie
<pb facs="tcp:170210:5"/> therein, ſurely this Mythologie is a Cabinet which needeth no key to unlock it, the lid or cover lyeth open.</p>
            <p>Let me intreate you Sir to put your hana into this Cabinet, and after therein you finde what may pleaſe or content you, the ſame will be as much contentment unto your</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>True Friend, J. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170210:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ANTHEOLOGIA,</hi> OR The Speech of Flowers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was a place in <hi>Theſſaly</hi> (and I am ſorry to ſay there <hi>was</hi> a place in <hi>Theſſaly,</hi> for though the place be there ſtill, yet it is not it ſelfe. The <hi>bones</hi> thereof remaine, not the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Colour.</hi> The ſtandards of <hi>Hilles</hi> and <hi>Rivers;</hi> not the Ornaments of <hi>Woods, Bowers, Groves</hi> and <hi>Banqueting-houſes.</hi> Theſe long
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170210:6"/> ſince are defaced by the <hi>Turkes,</hi> whoſe barbarous natures wage warre with civility it ſelfe, and take a delight to make a <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe</hi> where before their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt they found a <hi>Paradiſe.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This place is ſome five miles in length, and though the breadth bee Corrivall with the length to equallize the ſame, and may ſo ſeeme at the firſt ſight; yet it falleth ſhort upon exact examimination, as extending but to foure miles. This place was by the Poets called <hi>Tempe,</hi> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement of Earthly happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhewing that in <hi>ſhort hand,</hi> which the whole world preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170210:6"/> in a <hi>larger character,</hi> no earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſure was elſewhere affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but here it might be found in the heighth thereof.</p>
            <p>Within this Circuit of ground, there is ſtill extant, by the rare preſervation of the owner, a ſmall Scantlin of ſome three Acres, which I might call the Tempe of Tempe, and re-epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomiz'd the delicacies of all the reſt. It was divided into a <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> in the <hi>upper</hi> Part whereof <hi>Flowers</hi> did grow, in the <hi>lower, Hearbs,</hi> and thoſe of all ſorts and kinds. And now in Spring time earth did put on her new cloathes, though had ſome cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Herald</hi> beheld the ſame,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170210:7"/> he would have condemned her <hi>Coate</hi> to have been of no antient <hi>bearing,</hi> it was ſo overcharged with variety of <hi>Colours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For there was <hi>yellow Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>golds, Wallflowers, Auriculuſſes, Gold Knobs,</hi> and abundance of other nameleſſe <hi>Flowers,</hi> which would poſe a <hi>Nomenclator</hi> to call them by their diſtinct de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominations. There was <hi>White, the Dayes Eye, white roſes, Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes, &amp;c. Blew, Violet, Iriſſe, Red Roſes,</hi> Pionies, &amp;c. The whole field was <hi>vert</hi> or <hi>greene,</hi> and all colours were preſent ſave <hi>ſable,</hi> as too ſad and dolefull for ſo merry a meeting. All the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Flora</hi> being ſummoned
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170210:7"/> there, to make their appearance at a great ſolemnity.</p>
            <p>Nor was the lower part of the ground leſſe ſtored with herbs, and thoſe ſo various, that if <hi>Gerard</hi> himſelfe had bin in the place, upon the behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, he muſt have been forced to a re-edition of his <hi>Herball,</hi> to adde the recruit of thoſe <hi>Plants,</hi> which formerly were unſeen by him, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known unto him.</p>
            <p>In this ſolemn Randevouz of <hi>Flowers</hi> and <hi>Herbs,</hi> the <hi>Roſe</hi> ſtood forth, and made an <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to this effect.</p>
            <p>It is not unknown to you, how I have the precedency of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170210:8"/> all <hi>Flowers,</hi> confirmed unto me under the <hi>Patent</hi> of a double <hi>Sence, Sight, ſmell.</hi> What more curious <hi>Colours?</hi> how do all <hi>Diers bluſh</hi> when they behold my <hi>bluſhing,</hi> as conſcious to themſelves, that their <hi>Art</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imitate that tincture, which <hi>Nature</hi> hath ſtamped upon me. <hi>Smell,</hi> it is not luſciouſly <hi>offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive,</hi> nor dangerouſly <hi>Faint,</hi> but comforteth with a delight, and delighteth with the comfort thereof: Yea, when <hi>Dead,</hi> I am more Soveraigne then <hi>Living:</hi> What Cordials are made of my Syrups? how many corrupted Lungs (thoſe Fans of Nature) ſore waſted with conſumption,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170210:8"/> that they ſeem utterly unable any longer to cool the heat of the <hi>Heart,</hi> with their <hi>ventilati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> are with <hi>Conſerves</hi> made of my ſtamped <hi>Leaves,</hi> reſtored to their former ſoundneſſe againe: More would I ſay in mine own cauſe, but that happily I may be taxed of pride, and ſelfe-flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, who ſpeak much in mine own behalf, &amp; therefore I leave the reſt to the judgment of ſuch as hear me, and paſſe from this <hi>diſcourſe</hi> to my juſt <hi>complaint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is lately a <hi>Flower</hi> (ſhal I call it ſo? in courteſie I will tearme it ſo, though it deſerve not the appellation) a <hi>Toolip,</hi> which hath ingrafted the love
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170210:9"/> and affections of moſt people unto it; and what is this <hi>Toolip?</hi> a wellcomplexion'd ſtink, an ill ſavour wrapt up in pleaſant colours: As for the uſe thereof in <hi>Phyſick,</hi> no <hi>Phyſitian</hi> hath honoured it yet with the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor with a <hi>Greek,</hi> or <hi>Latin</hi> name, ſo inconſiderable hath it hitherto been accompted; and yet this is that which filleth all Gardens, hundred of pounds being given for the root there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whilſt I the <hi>Roſe,</hi> am negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and contemned, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived beneath the honour of noble hands, and ſit only to grow in the gardens of Yeomen I truſt the remainder to your
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170210:9"/> apprehenſions, to make out that, which grief for ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved injuries will not ſuffer me to expreſſe.</p>
            <p>Hereat the <hi>Roſe</hi> wept, and the dropping of her <hi>white</hi> tears down her <hi>red</hi> cheeks, ſo well becomed her, that if ever ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row was lovely, it then appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo, which moved the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to much compaſſion, her <hi>Tears</hi> ſpeaking more then her tongue, in her own behalfe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Tool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p</hi> ſtood up inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, as rather <hi>challenging</hi> then <hi>craving</hi> reſpect from the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of <hi>Flowers</hi> there preſent, &amp; thus vaunted it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>I am not ſolicitous what to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170210:10"/> returne to the complaint of this <hi>Roſe,</hi> whoſe own demerit hath juſtly outed it ſelf of that reſpect, which the miſtaken world formerly beſtowed upon it, and which mens eyes, now opened, juſtly reaſſume, and conferre on thoſe who better deſerve the ſame. To ſay that I am not more worthy then the <hi>Roſe,</hi> what is it, but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne mankind, and to arraign the moſt <hi>Gentle</hi> and knowing among men of ignorance, for miſplacing their affections: Surely <hi>Vegetables</hi> muſt not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to mount above <hi>Rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> creatures, or to think that men are not the moſt compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170210:10"/> judges of the worth and valew of <hi>Flowers.</hi> I confeſſe there is yet no known ſoveraign vertue in my leaves, but it is injurious to inferre that I have none, becauſe as yet not taken notice of. If we ſhould exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine <hi>all,</hi> by their intrinſick va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lews, how many contemptible things in Nature would take the upper-hand of thoſe which are moſt valued; by this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a <hi>Flint-ſtone</hi> would be better then a <hi>Diamond,</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining that ſpark of fire there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, whence men with combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible matter may heat them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the coldeſt ſeaſon: and cleer it is, that the <hi>Load-ſtone,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170210:11"/> (that grand <hi>Pilot</hi> to the <hi>North,</hi> which findeth the way there in the darkeſt night) is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the moſt orient Pearle in the world: But they will generally be condemned for unwiſe, who prize things according to this proportion.</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore in ſtones and minerals, that thoſe things are not moſt <hi>valued,</hi> which have moſt vertue, but that men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their eyes and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies raiſe the reputation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, let it not be interpreted to my diſadvantage, that I am not eminently known for any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall operation; perchance the diſcovery hereof is reſerved for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170210:11"/> the next age, to find out the <hi>latent</hi> vertue which <hi>lurketh</hi> in me: And this I am confident of, that <hi>Nature</hi> would never have hung out ſo gorgious a ſigne, if ſome gueſt of quality had not been lodged therein; ſurely my <hi>leaves,</hi> had never been <hi>feathered</hi> with ſuch variety of <hi>colours,</hi> (which hath proclaimed me the King of all Lillies) had not ſome ſtrange vertue, whereof the world is yet ignorant, been treaſured up therein.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Roſe,</hi> let her thank her ſelfe, if ſhe be ſenſible of any decay in eſteem, I have not am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly affected ſuperiority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove her, nor have I fraudulent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170210:12"/> endevoured to ſupplant her: only I ſhould have been want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my ſelfe, had I refuſed thoſe favours from <hi>Ladies,</hi> which their importunity hath preſſed upon me: And may the <hi>Roſe</hi> remember, how ſhe out of cauſeleſſe jealouſie, maketh all hands to be her enemies that gather her; what need is there that ſhe ſhould gariſon her ſelfe within her prickles? why muſt ſhe ſet ſo many Thornes to lye conſtant <hi>perdue,</hi> that none muſt gather her, but ſuch as ſuddenly ſurprize her; and do not all that crop her, run the hazard of hurting their fingers: This is that which hath weaned the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170210:12"/> world from her love, whilſt my ſmooth ſtalk expoſing <hi>Ladies</hi> to no ſuch perills, hath made them by exchange to fix their removed affections upon me.</p>
            <p>At this ſtood up the <hi>Violet,</hi> and all prepared themſelves with reſpectfull attention, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring the <hi>Violet</hi> for the Age thereof, for the <hi>Prim Roſe</hi> alone excepted, it is <hi>Seignior</hi> to all the <hi>Flowers</hi> in the year, and was highly regarded for the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the experience thereof that durſt encounter the cold, and had paſt many bitter blaſts, whereby it had gained much wiſpome, and had procured a venerable reſpect, both to his <hi>perſon</hi> and <hi>Counſell.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170210:13"/>
            <p>The caſe (ſaith the <hi>Violet)</hi> is not of particular concernment, but extendeth it ſelfe to the life and liberty of all the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Flowers;</hi> the complaint of the <hi>Roſe</hi> we muſt all acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be juſt and true, and ever ſince I could remember, we have paid the <hi>Roſe</hi> a juſt <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute</hi> of <hi>Fealty</hi> as our Prime and principall As for this <hi>Toolip,</hi> it hath not been in <hi>being</hi> in our <hi>Garden</hi> above theſe ſixty years: Our <hi>Fathers</hi> never knew that ſuch a <hi>Flower</hi> would be, and perhaps our children may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver know it ever was; what traveller brought it hither: I know not; they ſay it is of a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170210:13"/> 
               <hi>Syrian</hi> extraction, but ſure there it grew wild in the open fields, and is not beheld otherwiſe, then a gentler ſort of weed: But we may obſerve that all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forraign <hi>vices</hi> are made <hi>vertues</hi> in this countrey, forraign <hi>drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe</hi> is Grecian <hi>Mirth</hi> (thence the proverb, <hi>The merry Greek)</hi> forraign <hi>pride,</hi> Grecian <hi>good behaviour;</hi> forraign <hi>luſt,</hi> Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>love;</hi> forraign <hi>lazineſse,</hi> Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian <hi>harmeleſsneſse;</hi> forraign <hi>weeds,</hi> Grecian <hi>Flowers.</hi> My judgement therefore is, that if we do not ſpeedily eradicate this <hi>intruder</hi> (this <hi>Toolip)</hi> in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of time will out us all of our juſt poſſeſſions, ſeeing no
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170210:14"/> 
               <hi>Flower</hi> can pretend a cleerer title then the <hi>Roſe</hi> hath; and let us every one make the caſe to be his owne.</p>
            <p>The gravity of the <hi>Violet</hi> ſo prevailed with the <hi>Senate</hi> of <hi>Flowers,</hi> that all concurred with his judgment herein; and ſuch who had not the faculty of the fluentneſſe of their tongues to expreſſe themſelves in large <hi>Orations,</hi> thought that the well managing of a <hi>yea,</hi> or <hi>nay,</hi> ſpoke them as well wiſhing to the generall good, as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing themſelves in large <hi>Harrangues;</hi> and theſe ſoberly concluded, that the <hi>Toolip</hi> ſhould be rooted out of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170210:14"/> Garden, and caſt on the <hi>dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill,</hi> as one who had juſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded a place not due there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and this accordingly was performed.</p>
            <p>Whilſt this was paſſing in the <hi>upper houſe</hi> of the <hi>Flowers,</hi> no leſs were the tranſactions in the lower houſe of the <hi>herbs;</hi> where there was a generall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation againſt <hi>Wormewood,</hi> the generality condemning it, as fitter to grow in a <hi>ditch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> then in a <hi>Garden: Wormewood</hi> hardly received leave to make its own defence, pleading in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for its innocency.</p>
            <p>I would gladly know whom I have offended in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170210:15"/> of <hi>Herbs,</hi> that there ſhould be ſo generall a conſpiracy againſt me? only two things can be charged on me, <hi>commonneſſe</hi> and <hi>bitterneſſe;</hi> if <hi>commonneſſe</hi> paſs for a fault, you may arraign <hi>Nature</hi> it ſelf, and condemn the beſt Jewels thereof, the <hi>light</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> the <hi>benefit</hi> of the <hi>Ayre,</hi> the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity</hi> of the <hi>Water,</hi> are not theſe ſtaple commodities of mankind, without which no being or ſubſiſtance: if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be my charity to ſtoop ſo low, as to tender my ſelfe to every place for the publique ſervice, ſhall that for which I deſerve, if not praiſe, I need no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170210:15"/> pardon, be charged upon me as an offence.</p>
            <p>As for my <hi>bitterneſse,</hi> it is not a malitious &amp; miſchievous <hi>bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> to do hurt, but a helpfull &amp; medicinall <hi>bitterneſſe,</hi> whereby many cures are effected. How many have ſurfeited on honey? how many have dig'd their gravs in a Sugar-loaf? how many diſeaſes have bin cauſed by the <hi>dulcor</hi> of many luſcious ſweet-meats? then am I ſent for <hi>Phyſitian</hi> to theſe patients, and with my brother <hi>Cardus</hi> (whom you behold with a loving eye, I ſpeak not this to endanger him, but to defend my ſelfe) reſtore them (if temperate in any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170210:16"/> and perſwaded by their friends to taſt of us) unto their former health. I ſay no more, but were all my patients now my pleaders, were all thoſe who have gained <hi>health by me,</hi> preſent to <hi>intercede for me,</hi> I doubt not but to be reinſtated in your good opinions.</p>
            <p>True it is, I am condemned for over<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hot, and too paſſionate in my operation; but are not the beſt natures ſubject to this diſtemper? is it not obſerved that the moſt <hi>witty</hi> are the moſt <hi>cholerick?</hi> a little over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing is <hi>pardonable,</hi> I will not ſay neceſſary in this kind, nor let me be condemned as deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170210:16"/> to the <hi>ſight,</hi> having ſuch good opening, and <hi>abſtergent</hi> qualities, that moderately ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, eſpecially in a <hi>Morning,</hi> I am both <hi>food</hi> and <hi>Phyſick</hi> for a <hi>forenoon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſtrange to ſee how <hi>paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>ſelfe-intereſt</hi> ſway in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, more then the juſtice and merit of a cauſe; it was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily expected that <hi>Worm-wood</hi> ſhould have been acquitted, and re-admitted a <hi>member</hi> in the <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety</hi> of <hi>Herbs:</hi> But what will not a <hi>Faction</hi> carry; <hi>Worme-woods</hi> friends were caſually abſent that very day, making merry at an entertainment; her enemies (let not that <hi>Sex</hi> be angry for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170210:17"/> making <hi>Wormwood</hi> feminine) appeared in a full body, and made ſo great a noiſe, as if ſome <hi>mouths</hi> had two <hi>tongues</hi> in them, and though ſome engaged very zealouſly in <hi>Wormwoods</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, yet over-charged with the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of <hi>Number,</hi> it was carryed in the <hi>Negative,</hi> that <hi>Wormwood, alias abſynthium,</hi> ſhould be pluckt up root and branch from the <hi>Garden,</hi> and thrown upon the <hi>Dunghill,</hi> which was done accordingly, where it had the wofull ſociety of the <hi>Toolip,</hi> in this happy, that being equally miſerable, they might be a comfort the one to the other, and ſpent many
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170210:17"/> howers in mutuall recounting their ſeverall calamities, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing each to exceed the other in the relation thereof.</p>
            <p>Let us now amidſt much ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs interweave ſomething of more mirth and pleaſantneſſe in the <hi>Garden.</hi> There were <hi>two Roſes</hi> growing upon one <hi>Buſh,</hi> the one <hi>pale</hi> and <hi>wan</hi> with <hi>age,</hi> ready to drop off, as uſefull on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a <hi>Still:</hi> the other a young <hi>Bud,</hi> newly looſened from its <hi>green ſwadling cloaths,</hi> and pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping on the riſing Sun, it ſeem'd by its orient colour to be died by the reflection therof.</p>
            <p>Of theſe, the aged <hi>Roſe</hi> thus began.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170210:18"/>
            <p>Siſter <hi>Bud,</hi> learn <hi>witt</hi> by my <hi>woe,</hi> and cheaply enjoy the <hi>free</hi> and <hi>ful</hi> benefit of that purchaſe which coſt me <hi>dear</hi> and <hi>bitter</hi> experience: Once I was like your ſelfe, young and pretty, ſtraitly laced in my <hi>gree-Girdle,</hi> not ſwoln to that breadth and corpulency which now you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in me, every hand which paſſed by me courted me, and perſons of all ſorts were ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to gather me: How many fair fingers of curious Ladies tendred themſelves to remove me from the place of my abode; but in thoſe daies I was coy, &amp; to tell you plainly fooliſh, I ſtood on mine own defence,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170210:18"/> ſummoned my <hi>life-guard</hi> about me, commanded every prickle as ſo many <hi>Halberdeers,</hi> to ſtand to their <hi>Armes,</hi> defie thoſe that durſt touch me, proteſted my ſelfe a votary of conſtant virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; frighted hereat, paſſengers deſiſted from their intentions to crop me, and left me to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the ſullen humour of my own reſervedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Afterwards the Sun beams wrought powerfully upon me, (eſpecialy about noon-time) to this my preſent extent, the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rient colour</hi> which bluſhed ſo beautifull in me at the firſt, was much abated, with an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture of <hi>wanneſs</hi> and <hi>paleneſs</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170210:19"/> therewith, ſo that the <hi>Green</hi> (or white ſickneſſe rather, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pennance for over-kept virginity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> began to infect me, and that fragrant ſent of mine, began to remit and leſſen the ſweetneſſe thereof, and I daily decayed in my naturall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume; thus ſeeing I daily leſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the repute of all eyes and noſtrills, I began too late to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent my ſelfe of my former frowardneſſe; and ſought that my diligence by an after-game; ſhould recover what my folly had loſt; I pranked up my ſelfe to my beſt advantage, ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all my ſweetneſſe to appear in the height thereof, recruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170210:19"/> my decayed <hi>Colour,</hi> by bluſhing for my own folly, and wooed every hand that paſſed by me, to remove me.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe in ſome ſort it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers rape to a Maiden modeſty, if forgetting their ſex, they that ſhould be all <hi>Ears,</hi> turn mouthes, they that ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, offer; when we women, who only ſhould be the paſſive <hi>Counterparts</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive impreſſion from others, boldly preſume to ſtamp them on others, and by an inverted method of nature, turn plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders unto men, and wooe them for their affections. For all this there is but one excuſe, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170210:20"/> that is abſolute neceſsity, which as it breaks through ſtone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walls, ſo no wonder if in this caſe it alters and tranſpoſes the <hi>Sexes,</hi> making women to <hi>man it</hi> in caſe of extremity, when men are wanting to tender their affections unto them.</p>
            <p>All was but in vaine, I was entertained with ſcorne and neglect, the <hi>hardned</hi> hands of <hi>dayly Labourers, brawned</hi> with continuall work, the <hi>black</hi> hands of <hi>Moores,</hi> which alwaies carry <hi>Night</hi> in their <hi>Faces,</hi> ſleighted and contemned me; yea, now behold my laſt hope is but to deck and adorn houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and to be laid as a propertie
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170210:20"/> in windowes, till at laſt I die in the <hi>Hoſpitall</hi> of ſome <hi>ſtill,</hi> where when uſeleſs for any thing elſe, we are generally admitted. And now my very <hi>leaves</hi> begin to <hi>leave</hi> me, and I to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted and forſaken of my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>O how happy are thoſe <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> who are preferred in their youths; to be warme in the hands and breaſts of faire La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, who are joyned together with other <hi>flowers</hi> of <hi>ſeverall kinds</hi> in a <hi>Poſie,</hi> where the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reſult of ſweetneſſe from them all, raviſheth the <hi>Smel</hi> by an intermixture of various co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, all united by their <hi>ſtalks</hi> within the ſame <hi>thred</hi> that bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170210:21"/> them together.</p>
            <p>Therefore Siſter <hi>Bud</hi> grow wiſe by my folly, and know it is far greater happineſſe to loſe thy <hi>Virginity</hi> in a good hand, then to wither on the <hi>ſtalk</hi> whereon thou groweſt: accept of thy firſt and beſt tender, leſt afterwards in vaine thou court eſt the reverſion of fragments of that feaſt of love, which firſt was freely tendred unto thee.</p>
            <p>Leave we them in their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and proceed to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the <hi>Toolip</hi> and <hi>Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> now in a moſt pitifull condition, as they were lying on the <hi>Dunghill;</hi> behold a <hi>vaſt Giant Boar</hi> comes unto them;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170210:21"/> that which <hi>Hercules</hi> was ſaid to kill, and which was accounted by ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>foreman</hi> of the <hi>jury</hi> of his <hi>Labours,</hi> was but a <hi>Pygmie,</hi> or rather but a <hi>Pig,</hi> in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this; and with his <hi>Tusks</hi> wherewith <hi>Nature</hi> had armed him to be his ſword as his <hi>ſhoulders</hi> are his ſhield he began to rend and tear the <hi>Toolip</hi> and <hi>Wormewood,</hi> who exclaimed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him as followeth.</p>
            <p>SIR,</p>
            <p>Pitty uſeth alwaies to be an attendant of a generous mind, &amp; valiant ſpirit, for which I have heard you much commended. <hi>Cruelty</hi> is commonly obſerved to keep company with <hi>Coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170210:22"/> and <hi>baſe minds,</hi> to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in <hi>cruell actions,</hi> behold we are the objects rather of your pitty, whoſe ſufferings may rather render us to the commiſeration of any that juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider our caſe. I the <hi>Too<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> by a <hi>faction</hi> of <hi>flowers,</hi> was outed of the <hi>Garden,</hi> where I have as good a right and title to abide as any other: and this <hi>Wormewood,</hi> notwithſtanding her <hi>just</hi> and long <hi>plea,</hi> how uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and cordiall ſhe was, was by a <hi>conſpiracy</hi> of <hi>Herbs</hi> excluded the <hi>Garden,</hi> and both of us igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniouſly confined to this place, where we muſt without all hopes quickly expire: Our
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170210:22"/> humble requeſt unto you is not to ſhorten thoſe few minutes of our lives which are left unto us, ſeeing ſuch prejudice was done to our <hi>Vitals</hi> (whe our roots were mangled by that cruel eradication) that there is an impoſſibility of our long continuance: Let us therefore fairly breath out our laſt breath, and antidate not our miſery, but let us have the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of a quiet cloſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</p>
            <p>But if ſo be that you are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the deſtruction of <hi>flowers</hi> and <hi>herbs,</hi> know the <hi>pleaſure</hi> and <hi>contentment</hi> therein muſt be far greater to root out
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170210:23"/> thoſe which are fairly <hi>flouriſhing</hi> in their <hi>prime,</hi> whereof plenty are in this <hi>Garden</hi> afforded, and if it pleaſe you to follow our directions, we will make you <hi>Maſter</hi> of a <hi>Paſſe,</hi> which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any difficulty ſhall convey you into the <hi>Garden;</hi> for though the ſame on all ſides almoſt is either <hi>walled</hi> or <hi>paled</hi> about, yet in one place it is fenced with a <hi>Hedge</hi> only, wherein, through the neglect of the <hi>Gardiner,</hi> (whoſe care it ought to be to ſecure the ſame) there is a <hi>hole</hi> left in ſuch capacity, as will yeeld you an eaſie entrance thereinto: There may you glut your ſelfe, and ſatiate your
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170210:23"/> ſoule with variety of <hi>Flowers</hi> and herbs, ſo that an <hi>Epicure</hi> might have cauſe to complain of the plenty thereof.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Boar</hi> apprehends the motion, is ſencible it was advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious for him, and following their directions, he makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe Maſter of his owne deſire. O the ſpitefulneſſe of ſome <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures!</hi> how do they <hi>wreck</hi> their their anger on all perſons: It was revenge for the <hi>Toolip</hi> and <hi>Wormwood,</hi> unleſſe they had ſpitefully wronged the whole <hi>Corporation</hi> of <hi>Flowers,</hi> out of which they were ejected as uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and dangerous <hi>Members:</hi> And now conſider how theſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170210:24"/> two <hi>pride</hi> themſelves in their own <hi>vindicative</hi> thoughts? how do they in their forerunning fancy antidate the death of all <hi>Herbs</hi> and <hi>Flowers.</hi> What is ſweeter then revenge? how do they pleaſe themſelves to ſee what are <hi>hot</hi> &amp; <hi>cold</hi> in the <hi>firſt, ſecond, third,</hi> and <hi>fourth degree,</hi> (which borders on poiſon) how all theſe different in their ſeverall <hi>Tempers,</hi> will be made <hi>friends</hi> in univerſall miſery, and <hi>compounded</hi> in a generall deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Little did either <hi>Flowers</hi> or <hi>Herbs</hi> think of the <hi>Boares</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, who were ſolacing themſelves with merry and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170210:24"/> pleaſant diſcourſe; and it will not be amiſs to deceive time, by inſerting the <hi>Courtſhip</hi> of <hi>Thrift</hi> a <hi>flower-Herb,</hi> unto the <hi>Mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gold,</hi> thus accoſting her, juſt as the <hi>Boar</hi> entered into the <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miſtreſſe,</hi> Of all <hi>Flowers</hi> that grow on Earth, give me leave to profeſſe my ſincereſt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to you: Complements have ſo infected mens tongues (and grown an <hi>Epidemicall fault,</hi> or as others eſteem it, a faſhionable accompliſhment) that we know not when they ſpeak truth, having made diſſembling their language, by a conſtant uſage thereof: But believe me <hi>Miſtriſs</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170210:25"/> my <hi>heart</hi> never entertained any other interpreter then my <hi>Tongue;</hi> and if there be a <hi>veine</hi> (which Anatomiſts have gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally avouched, carrying intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence from the <hi>heart</hi> to the <hi>lips)</hi> aſſure your ſelfe that <hi>vein</hi> acts now in my diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>I have taken ſignall notice of your accompliſhments, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many other rare quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, particularly of this, your loyalty and faithfulneſſe to the <hi>Sun, Soveraign</hi> to all <hi>Vegetables,</hi> to whoſe warming <hi>Beams,</hi> we owe our <hi>being</hi> and <hi>increaſe:</hi> ſuch your love thereunto, that you attend his <hi>riſing,</hi> and therewith <hi>open,</hi> and at his ſetting <hi>ſhut</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170210:25"/> your <hi>windowes:</hi> True it is, that <hi>Helitropium (or turner with the Sun)</hi> hath a long time been at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the <hi>Sun-flower,</hi> a voluminous Giant like <hi>Flower,</hi> of no vertue or worth as yet diſcovered therein, but we all know the many and Soveraign vertues in your leaves, the <hi>Herb generall in all pottage:</hi> Nor do you as <hi>Herb John</hi> ſtand newter, and as too many now adaies in our <hi>Commonwealth</hi> do, neither good nor ill (expecting to be acted on by the impreſsion of the prevailent party) and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe warily engage not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but you really appear ſoveraign and operative in your
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170210:26"/> wholeſome effects: The conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration hereof, and no other by reflection, hath moved me to the tender of my affections, which if it be candidly <hi>reſented,</hi> as it is ſincerely offered, I doubt not but it may conduce to the mutuall happineſſe of us both.</p>
            <p>Beſides know (though I am the unpropereſt perſon to trumpet forth my owne praiſe) my <hi>name</hi> is <hi>Thrift,</hi> and my <hi>nature</hi> anſwereth thereunto; I doe not prodigally waſt thoſe Lands in a <hi>moment,</hi> which the induſtry and frugality of my Anceſtors hath in a long time advanced; I am no gamſter to ſhake away with a <hi>quaking</hi> hand, what a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170210:26"/> more <hi>fixed</hi> hand did gain and acquire: I am none of thoſe who in variety of cloaths, bury my quick eſtate as in a winding ſheet; nor am I one of thoſe who by cheats and deceits im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove my ſelfe on the loſſes of others; no <hi>Widowes</hi> have wept, no <hi>Orphans</hi> have cryed for what I have offered unto them (this is not <hi>Thrift</hi> but rather <hi>Felony)</hi> nor owe I any thing to my own body; I fear not to be arreſted upon the <hi>action</hi> of my own car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſe, as if my creditors ſhould cunningly compact there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and quit ſcores, reſigning their Bill and Bond unto mine own body, whilſt that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170210:27"/> ſurrendereth all obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations for food and cloaths thereunto: Nor do I undertake to buy out <hi>Bonds</hi> in <hi>controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> for almoſt nothing, that ſo running a ſmall hazard, I may gain great advantage, if my bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain therein prove ſucceſsfull. No, I am plain and honeſt <hi>Thrift,</hi> which none ever did, or will ſpeak againſt, ſave ſuch <hi>prodigall ſpend-thrifts,</hi> who in their reduced thoughts, will ſpeak more againſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>And now it is in your power to accept or refuſe what I have offered, which is the <hi>priviledg</hi> which nature hath allotted for your <hi>feminine ſex,</hi> which we men
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170210:27"/> perchance may grudg and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine at, but it being paſt our power to amend it, we muſt permit our ſelves as well as we may to the conſtant cuſtome prevailing herein.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Marigold</hi> demurely hung down her head, as not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fond of the motion, and kept ſilence ſo long as it might ſtand with the rule of manners, but at laſt brake forth into the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing return.</p>
            <p>I am tempted to have a good opinion of my ſelfe, to which all people are prone, and we women moſt of all, if we may beleeve your—of us, which herein I am affraid are too true:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170210:28"/> But Sir, I conceive my ſelfe too wiſe to be deceived by your commendations of me, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in ſo large a way, and on ſo generall an account, that other <hi>Flowers</hi> not only ſhare with me, but exceeed me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: May not the <hi>Daies-eye</hi> not only be <hi>corrivall</hi> with me; but <hi>ſuperior</hi> to me in that quality, wherein ſo much you praiſe me; my <hi>vigilancy ſtarteth</hi> only from the <hi>Suns riſing,</hi> hers <hi>bears date</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>dawning</hi> of the <hi>morning,</hi> &amp; out-runs my ſpeed by many degrees: my <hi>vertue</hi> in pottage which you ſo highly commend, impute it not to my <hi>Modeſty,</hi> but to my <hi>Guiltineſſe,</hi> if I cannot
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170210:28"/> give it entertainment; for how many hundred <hi>Herbs</hi> which you have neglected exceed me therein.</p>
            <p>But the plain truth is, you love not me for my ſelfe, but for your advantage: It is <hi>Gold</hi> on the <hi>arrear</hi> of my <hi>name</hi> which maketh <hi>Thrift</hi> to be my <hi>Suitor:</hi> how often, and how unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have you tendered your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, even to <hi>Penny-royall,</hi> it ſelfe, had ſhe not ſcorned to be courted by you.</p>
            <p>But I commend the Girle that ſhe knew her own worth, though it was but a <hi>penny,</hi> yet it is a <hi>Royall</hi> one, and therefore not a fit match for every baſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170210:29"/> 
               <hi>Suitor,</hi> but knew how to valew her ſelfe, and give me leave to tell you, that <hi>Matches</hi> founded on <hi>Covetouſneſſe</hi> never <hi>ſucceed: Profit</hi> is the <hi>Load-ſtone</hi> of your <hi>affections, Wealth,</hi> the <hi>attractive</hi> of your <hi>Love, Money</hi> the <hi>mover</hi> of your deſire; how many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds have engaged themſelves on theſe principles, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards have bemoaned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the ſame? But oh the uncertainty of wealth? how unable is it to expleate &amp; ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the mind of man: Such as caſt Anchor thereat, ſeldome find faſt ground, but are <hi>toſſed</hi> about with the <hi>Tempeſts</hi> of many <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbances;</hi> theſe <hi>Wives</hi> for <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170210:29"/> of <hi>profit</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> (when there hath been no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nor higher intent) have filled all the world with <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief</hi> and <hi>miſery.</hi> Know then ſir, I return you a flat <hi>deniall,</hi> a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall</hi> that <hi>vertually</hi> contains ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, yea as many as ever I ſhall be able to pronounce: My tongue knowes no other language to you but <hi>No;</hi> ſcore it upon wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens diſſimulation (whereof we are too guilty, and I at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times as faulty as any) but Sir, read my eyes, my face, and compound all together, and know theſe are the expreſsions dictated from my heart; I ſhall embrace a thouſand deaths
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170210:30"/> ſooner, then your Marriage-Bed.</p>
            <p>Thus were they harmeleſsly diſcourſing, and feared no ill, when on a ſudden they were ſurprized with the uncouth ſight of the <hi>Boare,</hi> which had entered their <hi>Garden,</hi> following his preſcribed directions, and armed with the <hi>Corſlet</hi> of his <hi>Briſtles, vaunted</hi> like a trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant <hi>Conqueror</hi> round about the <hi>Garden,</hi> as one who would firſt make them ſuffer in their <hi>fear,</hi> before in their feeling; how did he pleaſe himſelfe in the variety of the <hi>fears</hi> of the <hi>flowers,</hi> to ſee how ſome <hi>pale</hi> ones looked <hi>red,</hi> and ſome <hi>red</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170210:30"/> ones looked <hi>pale;</hi> leaving it to <hi>Philoſophers</hi> to <hi>diſpute</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide</hi> the different effects ſhould proceed from the ſame cauſes; and among all <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> commending the queſtion to the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> who becauſe they pretend an <hi>Antipathy,</hi> that they themſelves would never be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, never be mounted above the <hi>modell</hi> of a common uſuall <hi>Temper,</hi> are moſt competent <hi>Judges,</hi> impartially to give the reaſon of the cauſes of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of others.</p>
            <p>And now it is ſtrange to ſee the ſeverall waies the <hi>Flowers</hi> embraced to provide for their owne ſecurity; there is no ſuch
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170210:31"/> 
               <hi>Teacher</hi> as <hi>extremity; neceſſity</hi> hath found out more <hi>Arts,</hi> then ever ingenuity invented: The <hi>Wall-Gilly flower</hi> ran up to the top of the Wall of the <hi>Garden,</hi> where it hath grown ever ſince, and will never deſcend till it hath good ſecurity for its own ſafety; and being mounted thereon, he entertained the <hi>Boar</hi> with the following diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>Thou baſeſt and unworthieſt of <hi>four-footed Beaſts;</hi> thy <hi>Mother</hi> the <hi>Sow,</hi> paſſeth for the moſt contemptible <hi>name,</hi> that can be fixed on any <hi>She:</hi> Yea, <hi>Pliny</hi> reporteth, that a <hi>Sow</hi> growne <hi>old,</hi> uſeth to feed on her owne
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170210:31"/> 
               <hi>young;</hi> and herein I beleeve that <hi>Pliny,</hi> who otherwiſe might be ſtraitned for <hi>fellow-witneſſes,</hi> might find ſuch who will atteſt the truth of what he hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Mens <hi>Excrements</hi> is thy ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and what more cleanly creatures do ſcorn and deteſt, makes a feaſt for thee; nothing comes amiſſe unto thy mouth, and we know the proverb what can make a pan-cake unto thee: Now you are gotten into the <hi>Garden</hi> (ſhame light on that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligent <hi>Gardner,</hi> whoſe care it was to fence the ſame, by whoſe negligence and overſight, you have gotten an entrance into this <hi>Academy</hi> of <hi>Flowers</hi> and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170210:32"/> 
               <hi>Herbs)</hi> let me who am your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie give you ſome <hi>Counſell,</hi> and <hi>neglect</hi> it not, becauſe it comes from my <hi>Mouth.</hi> You ſee I am without the reach of your <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> and all your power cannot hurt me, except you be pleaſed to borrow <hi>wings</hi> from ſome <hi>Bird,</hi> thereby to advantage your ſelfe, to reach my habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Counſell</hi> therefore to you is this, be not <hi>Proud</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are <hi>Proſperous;</hi> who would ever have thought, that you could have entered this place, which we conceived was impregnable againſt any of your kind: Now becauſe you
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170210:32"/> have had ſucceſſe as farre above our <hi>expectations,</hi> as your <hi>deſerts;</hi> ſhow your own moderation in the uſage thereof; to <hi>Maſter</hi> us is eaſie, to <hi>Maſter</hi> your ſelfe is difficult. Attempt therefore that which as it is moſt <hi>hard</hi> to <hi>performe,</hi> ſo will it bring moſt <hi>honour</hi> to you when <hi>executed;</hi> and know, I ſpeak not this in relation to my ſelfe (ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly priviledged from your <hi>Tusks)</hi> but as <hi>acted</hi> with a <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſpirit,</hi> for the good of the <hi>Comminalty</hi> of <hi>Flowers;</hi> and if any thing hereafter betide you, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then you expect, you will remember that I am a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and foretell that which too late
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170210:33"/> you will credit and beleeve.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Boar</hi> heard the words, and entertained them with a <hi>ſurly ſilence,</hi> as conceiving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be <hi>mounted</hi> above dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſometimes he pittied the ſillineſſe of the <hi>Wall-flower,</hi> that pittyed him, and ſometimes he vowed revenge, concluding that the <hi>ſtones</hi> of the <hi>Wall</hi> would not afford it ſufficiont moiſture, for its conſtant dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling there, but that he ſhould take it for an advantage, when it deſcended for more ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>It is hard to expreſſe the <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> fear in the reſt of the <hi>flowers,</hi> and eſpecially the <hi>ſmall
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170210:33"/> Prim-roſes,</hi> begged of their <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> that they might retreat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the middle of them, which would only make them grow bigger and broader, and it would grieve a pittifull heart to hear the child plead, and the mother ſo often deny.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Child began;</hi> dear <hi>Mother,</hi> ſhe is but halfe a <hi>Mother</hi> that doth <hi>breed</hi> and not <hi>preſerve,</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>bring forth,</hi> and then to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us to worldly <hi>miſery, leſſens</hi> your <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>doubles</hi> our <hi>ſufferings:</hi> See how this tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall <hi>Boare</hi> threatens our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant undoing; I deſire only a <hi>Sanctuary</hi> in your <hi>boſome,</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating place into your <hi>breaſt,</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:170210:34"/> and who fitter to come into you, then ſhe that came out of you; whether ſhould we return, then from whence we came, it will be but one happineſſe, or one misfortune, together we ſhall die, or together be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; only ſome content and comfort will be unto me, either to be happy or unhappy in your company.</p>
            <p>The broader <hi>Prim-roſe</hi> heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto theſe words with a ſad countenance, as ſenſible in her ſelfe, that had not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent neceſſity hardned her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, ſhe neither would nor could return a deaf eare to ſo equall a motion. But now ſhe rejoyned.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170210:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Child,</hi> none can be more ſenſible then my ſelfe of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly affections, it troubles me more for me to deny thee, then for thee to be denyed; I love thy ſafety where it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily included in my dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the entertaining of thee will be my ruine and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; how many Parents in this age have been undone meerly for affording houſe and home to ſuch Children, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition might be quarrel'd with as expoſed to exception.</p>
            <p>I am ſure of mine owne inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, which never in the leaſt degree have offended this <hi>Boar,</hi> and therefore hope he will not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170210:35"/> offend me; what wrong and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury you have done him is beſt known to your ſelfe; ſtand therefore on your own bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, maintain your own inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; for my part I am reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not to be drowned for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hanging on me, but I will try as long as I can the ſtrength of my own armes and leggs; excuſe me good child, it is not <hi>hatred</hi> to you, but <hi>love</hi> to my ſelfe, which makes me to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand my own intereſt. The younger <hi>Prim-roſe</hi> returned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mother,</hi> I muſt again appeal to your affections, deſpairing to find any other <hi>Judge</hi> to Father my cauſe; remember I am part
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170210:35"/> of your ſelfe, and have never by any undutifulneſſe diſobliged your affections; I profeſſe alſo mine own integrity, that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have offended this <hi>Boar,</hi> being more innocent therein then your ſelfe, for alas my ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der years intitles me not to any correſpondency with him, this is the firſt minute (and may it be the laſt) that ever I beheld him; I reaſſume therefore my ſuite, ſuppoſing that your firſt denyall proceeded only from a deſire to try my importunity, and give me occaſion to enforce my requeſt with the greater earneſtneſſe: By your motherly bowels I conjure you (an exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170210:36"/> which (I beleeve) comes not within the compaſſe of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition) that you tenderme in this my extremity, whoſe greateſt ambition is to die in thoſe armes from whence I firſt fetcht my originall. And then ſhe left her <hi>tears</hi> ſingly to drop out the remainder, what her <hi>tongue</hi> could not expreſſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Affections</hi> of Parents may ſometimes be <hi>ſmothered,</hi> but ſeldome <hi>quenched,</hi> and mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the <hi>blaſt</hi> or <hi>bellowes</hi> from the ſubmiſſive mouthes of their <hi>Children,</hi> it quickly <hi>blazeth</hi> into a <hi>flame. Mother</hi> and <hi>daughter</hi> are like Tallies, one exactly anſwereth the other: The <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170210:36"/> Prim-roſe</hi> could no longer reſiſt the violence of her daughters importunity, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens her boſome for the preſent reception thereof, wherein ever ſince it hath grown doubled unto this day; and yet a double miſchief did ariſe from this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the <hi>Prim-roſe,</hi> or inſerting of the little one into the Bowels thereof.</p>
            <p>Firſt, thoſe <hi>Prim-roſes</hi> ever ſince grow very ſlowly, and <hi>lag</hi> the laſt among all the <hi>Flowers</hi> of that kind; ſingle <hi>Prim-roſes</hi> beat them out of diſtance, and are arrived at their <hi>Mark</hi> a month before the other <hi>ſtart</hi> out of their <hi>green leaves:</hi> yet it
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170210:37"/> will not be hard to aſſigne a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall cauſe thereof, namely, a greater power of the <hi>Sun</hi> is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to the production of greater <hi>Flowers,</hi> ſmall degrees of <hi>heat</hi> will ſuffice to give a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſingle <hi>Flowers,</hi> whilſt double ones groaning under the weight of their own great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, require a greater force of the <hi>Sun-beams</hi> to quicken them, and to ſpurre their <hi>lazineſſe,</hi> to make them appear out of their roots.</p>
            <p>But the ſecond <hi>Miſchief</hi> moſt concernes us, which is this, all ſingle <hi>Flowers</hi> are <hi>ſweeter,</hi> then thoſe that are double; and here we could wiſh that a <hi>Jury</hi> of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170210:37"/> 
               <hi>Floriſts</hi> were <hi>impannelled,</hi> not to eat, untill ſuch time as they were agreed in their <hi>verdict,</hi> what is the true cauſe thereof. Some will ſay that ſingle <hi>leaves</hi> of <hi>Flowers,</hi> being more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally wrought on by the <hi>Sun-Beams,</hi> are rarified thereby, and ſo all their ſweetneſſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume the more fully extracted; whereas double <hi>Flowers</hi> who lie as it were in a lump, and heap crouded together with its own <hi>leaves,</hi> the <hi>Sun-beams</hi> hath not that advantage ſingly to diſtill them, and to improve e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular <hi>leaf</hi> to the beſt advantage of ſweetneſſe: This ſure I am, that the old <hi>Prim-roſe</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:170210:38"/> ſencible of the abatement of her ſweetneſſe, ſince ſhe was <hi>clogged</hi> with the entertainment of her <hi>Daughter,</hi> halfe repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſhe had received her, returned this complaining diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daughter,</hi> I am ſencible that that the <hi>ſtatutes</hi> of <hi>inmates,</hi> was founded on very good and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid grounds, that many ſhould not be multiplyed within the roof of one and the ſame houſe, finding the inconveniency thereof by lodging thee my owne <hi>Daughter</hi> within my <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome;</hi> I wil not ſpeak how much I have loſt of my grouth, the <hi>Clock</hi> whereof is <hi>ſet back</hi> a whole
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170210:38"/> month by receiving of you; but that which moſt grieveth me, I perceive I am much abated in my <hi>ſweetneſſe</hi> (the eſſence of all <hi>Flowers)</hi> and which only di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth them from <hi>weeds,</hi> ſeeing otherwiſe in <hi>Colours, weeds</hi> may conteſt with us in brightneſſe and variety.</p>
            <p>Peace Mother (replyed the ſmall <hi>Prim-roſe)</hi> conceive not this to be your particular un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſſe, which is the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>accident</hi> falling out daily in common experience, namely, that the bigger and thicker <hi>people</hi> grow in their <hi>eſtates,</hi> the worſe and leſſe vertuous they are in their <hi>Converſations,</hi> our
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170210:39"/> age may produce millions of theſe inſtances; I knew ſome tenne years ſince many honeſt men, whoſe converſe was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar and faire, how did they court and deſire the company of their neighbours, and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, how was their company deſired by them? how <hi>humble</hi> were they in their <hi>carriage, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> in their <hi>expreſſions,</hi> and <hi>friendly</hi> in their <hi>behaviour,</hi> drawing the love and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all that were acquainted with them? But ſince being grown wealthy, they have firſt learnt not to know <hi>themſelves,</hi> and afterwards none of their <hi>neighbours;</hi> the <hi>brightneſſe</hi> of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170210:39"/> much <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> hath with the <hi>ſhine</hi> and <hi>luſtre</hi> thereof ſo <hi>perſtringed</hi> and <hi>dazled</hi> their <hi>eyes,</hi> that they have forgotten thoſe with whom they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſo familiar converſation; how <hi>proudly</hi> do they <hi>walk?</hi> how <hi>ſuperc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liouſly</hi> do they <hi>look?</hi> how <hi>diſdainfully</hi> do they <hi>ſpeak?</hi> they will not know their own <hi>Brothers</hi> and <hi>kindred,</hi> as being a <hi>kin</hi> only to themſelves.</p>
            <p>Indeed ſuch who have long been gaining of wealth, and have ſlowly proceeded by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees therein, whereby they have learnt to mannage their minds, are not ſo palpably proud as others; but thoſe who
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170210:40"/> in an inſtant have been ſurpriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a vaſt eſtate, <hi>flowing</hi> in upon them from a <hi>fountain</hi> farre above their <hi>deſerts,</hi> not being able to wield their own great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, have been preſt under the weight of their own eſtates, and have manifeſted that their minds never knew how to be ſtewards of their wealth, by forgetting themſelves in the diſpoſing thereof.</p>
            <p>I beleeve the little <hi>Prim-roſe</hi> would have beee longer in her diſcourſe, had not the approach of the <hi>Boar</hi> put an unexpected period thereunto, and made her break off her ſpeech before the ending thereof.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170210:40"/>
            <p>Now whilſt all other <hi>flowers</hi> were ſtruck into a <hi>panick</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, only <hi>two,</hi> the <hi>Violet,</hi> and the <hi>Marygold</hi> continued their diſcourſe, which was not attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to their valour or hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe above other <hi>Flowers,</hi> but that caſually both of them grew together in the <hi>declivity</hi> of a depreſſed <hi>Valley,</hi> ſo that they ſaw not the <hi>Boar,</hi> nor were they ſenſible of their own mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, nor durſt others remove their ſtations to bring them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence thereof.</p>
            <p>Siſter <hi>Marigold</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let)</hi> you and I have continued theſe many daies in the conteſt which of our two <hi>colours</hi> are
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170210:41"/> the moſt honourable and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the <hi>Eye,</hi> I know what you can plead for your ſelfe, that your <hi>yellowneſſe</hi> is the <hi>Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> the <hi>Soveraign</hi> of moſt mens hearts, and eſteemed the pureſt of all <hi>mettals;</hi> I deny not the truth hereof: But know that as farre as the <hi>Skie</hi> ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that which is buried in the <hi>Bowels</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> ſo farre my blew <hi>colour</hi> exceedeth yours; what is oftner mentioned by the <hi>Poets</hi> then the <hi>azure Clouds?</hi> let <hi>Heraulds</hi> be made the <hi>Vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> and I appeal to <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard,</hi> whether the <hi>azure</hi> doth not carry it cleer above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>colours</hi> herein; <hi>Sable</hi> or
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170210:41"/> 
               <hi>Black</hi> affrights the <hi>beholders</hi> with the <hi>hue</hi> thereof, and minds them of the <hi>Funerall</hi> of their laſt friends, whom they had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred <hi>Vert</hi> or <hi>Green</hi> I confeſſe is a <hi>colour</hi> refreſhing the <hi>ſight,</hi> and wore commonly before the eyes of ſuch who have had a caſuall miſchance therein; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it is but the <hi>Livery</hi> of <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty,</hi> a young upſtart <hi>colour,</hi> as <hi>green heads,</hi> and <hi>green youth</hi> do paſſe in common experience. <hi>Red</hi> I confeſſe is a noble <hi>colour,</hi> but it hath too much of <hi>bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe</hi> therein, and affrighteth beholders with the memory thereof: My <hi>Blew</hi> is expoſed to no cavills and exceptions,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170210:42"/> wherein <hi>black</hi> and <hi>red</hi> are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately compounded, ſo that I participate of the perfections of them both: the over gaudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>red,</hi> which hath too much <hi>light</hi> and <hi>brightneſs</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, is reduced and tempered with ſuch a <hi>mixture</hi> of <hi>black,</hi> that the <hi>red</hi> is made <hi>stayed,</hi> but not <hi>ſad</hi> therewith, and the <hi>black</hi> kept from over-much melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, with a proportionable contemperation of <hi>red</hi> therein: This is the reaſon that in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the <hi>Violet</hi> or <hi>purple colour</hi> hath paſſed for the emblem of Magiſtracy, and the <hi>Robes</hi> of the antient Roman judges al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies died therewith.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:170210:42"/>
            <p>The <hi>Violet</hi> ſcarce arived at the middle of her diſcourſe, when the approach of the <hi>Boar</hi> put it into a terrible fear, nor was their any <hi>Herb</hi> or <hi>Flower</hi> in the whole <hi>Garden</hi> left unſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized with fear, ſave only <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Sage,</hi> which caſually grew in an <hi>Iſland</hi> ſurrounded with water from the reſt, and ſecured with a lock-bridge from the <hi>Boars</hi> acceſſe. <hi>Sage</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, accoſted <hi>Time in</hi> this Nature.</p>
            <p>Moſt fragrant Siſter, there needs no other argument to convince thy tranſcendent ſweetneſſe, ſave only the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing to the <hi>Bees</hi> (the moſt
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170210:43"/> competent judges in this kind) thoſe little <hi>Chymiſts,</hi> who through their natural <hi>Alembick, diſtill</hi> the ſweeteſt and uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt of <hi>Liquors,</hi> did not the commonneſſe and cheapneſſe thereof make it leſſe valued: Now theſe induſtrious <hi>Bees,</hi> the emblem of a common-wealth (or Monarchy rather, if the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived traditions of a <hi>Maſter-Bee</hi> be true) make their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant diet upon the; for though no <hi>Flower</hi> comes amiſſe to their palates, yet are they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to preferre thee above the reſt. Now Siſter <hi>Time,</hi> faine would I be ſatisfied of you ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall queries, which only <hi>Time</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170210:43"/> is able to reſolve. Whether or no do you think that the <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Turks</hi> wherein we live, (whoſe cruelty hath deſtroyed faire <hi>Tempe</hi> to the ſmall rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of theſe few Acres) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſay, do you think that their <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>greatneſs</hi> doth <hi>encreaſe, ſtand ſtill,</hi> or <hi>abate?</hi> I know <hi>Time</hi> that <hi>you are the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of truth,</hi> and the finder out of all truths myſteries; be open therefore and candid with me herein, and freely ſpeak your mind of the caſe propounded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Time</hi> very gravely caſting down the eyes thereof to the earth; Siſter <hi>Sage</hi> (ſaid ſhe) had you propounded any queſtion
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170210:44"/> within the ſphear or circuit of a <hi>Garden,</hi> of the <hi>heat</hi> or <hi>coolneſſe, drineſse</hi> or <hi>moiſture, vertue</hi> or <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration</hi> of <hi>flowers</hi> and <hi>Herbs,</hi> I ſhould not have demurred to return you a ſpeedy anſwer; but this is of that dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that my own ſafety locks up my lips, and commands my ſilence therein: I know your wiſdome <hi>Sage,</hi> whence you have gotten your name and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, this is not an age to truſt the neereſt of our relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with ſuch an important ſecreſie; what ever thoughts are concealed within the <hi>Cabinet</hi> of my own <hi>boſome,</hi> ſhall there be preſerved in their ſecret pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170210:44"/> without imparting them to any; my confeſſor himſelfe ſhall know my <hi>conſcience,</hi> but not my judgement in affaires of <hi>State:</hi> Let us comply with the preſent neceſſity, and lie at a cloſe poſture, knowing there be fencers even now about us, who will ſet upon us if our guards lye open: generall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes are ſuch to which I will confine my ſelfe: It is antient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, <hi>that the ſubtill man lurks in generall.</hi> But now give me leave, for honeſty it ſelfe, if de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to be ſafe, to take San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary therein.</p>
            <p>Let us enjoy our own hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, and be ſenſible of the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170210:45"/> favour indulged to us, that whereas all <hi>Tempe</hi> is defaced, this <hi>Garden</hi> ſtill ſurviveth in ſome tolerable condition of proſperity, and we eſpecially <hi>miled</hi> about, are fenced from forraign foes, better then the reſt; let it ſatisfie your ſoule that we peaceably poſſeſs this happineſſe, and I am ſorry that the luſtre thereof is ſet forth with ſo true a foile, as the cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of our neighbours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sage returned;</hi> Were I a blab of my mouth, whoſe ſecreſie was ever ſuſpected, then might you be cautious in communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating your mind unto me: But ſecrecy is that I can principally
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170210:45"/> boaſt of, it being the quality for which the common-wealth of <hi>Flowers</hi> choſe me their privy Councellor, what therefore is told me in this nature, is depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited as ſecurely, as thoſe <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> which formerly were laid up in the <hi>Temple</hi> of ſafety it ſelf; and therefore with all modeſt importunity, I reaſſume my ſuit, and deſire your judgment of the queſtion, whether the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh</hi> Tyranny is likely to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue any longer? for <hi>Time</hi> I know alone can give an anſwer to this queſtion.</p>
            <p>Being confident <hi>(ſaid Time)</hi> of your fidelity, I ſhall expreſſe my ſelfe in that freeneſſe unto
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170210:46"/> you, which I never as yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to any mortall: I am of that hopefull opinion, that the period of this barbarous nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons greatneſſe begins to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, my firſt reaſon is drawn from the viciſſitude and muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility which attends all earthly things; <hi>Bodies</hi> arrived at the <hi>verticall</hi> point of their <hi>ſtrength, decay</hi> and <hi>decline.</hi> The <hi>Moon</hi> when in the fulneſſe of its <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing,</hi> tendeth to a <hi>waning;</hi> it is a pitch too high for any ſubſunary thing to amount un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſtantly, to proceed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſively in greatneſſe; this maketh me to hope that this Giant-like <hi>Empire,</hi> cemented
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170210:46"/> with Tyranny, ſupported, not ſo much with their own poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as with the ſervility of ſuch who are under them, hath ſeen its beſt daies and higheſt eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>To this end, to come to more particulars, what was it which firſt made the <hi>Turks</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, in ſo ſhort a time to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-run all <hi>Greece,</hi> but theſe two things; firſt, the <hi>diſſentions,</hi> 2. the <hi>diſſoluteneſſe</hi> of your antient <hi>Greeks:</hi> Their <hi>diſſentions</hi> are too well known, the Emperor of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> being grown al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt but <hi>titular,</hi> ſuch the pride and potency of many Peeres under him. The <hi>Egean</hi> is not
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170210:47"/> more ſtored with <hi>Iſlands</hi> (as I think ſcarce ſuch a heap or hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle is to be found of them in all the world againe) as <hi>Greece</hi> was with ſeverall <hi>factions,</hi> the <hi>Epirots</hi> hated the <hi>Achayans,</hi> the <hi>Meſedans</hi> bandoned againſt the <hi>Thracians,</hi> the <hi>Dalmatians</hi> maintained <hi>deadly feud</hi> againſt the <hi>Wallachians:</hi> Thus was the conqueſt made eaſie for the <hi>Turks,</hi> beholding not ſo much to their own valour, as to the <hi>Grecian</hi> diſcord.</p>
            <p>Next to their <hi>diſsentions,</hi> their <hi>diſſoluteneſse</hi> did expedite their ruine; drunkenneſſe was ſo common among them, that it was a ſin to be ſober, ſo that I
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170210:47"/> may ſay, all <hi>Greece reel'd</hi> and <hi>ſtaggered</hi> with its own <hi>intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance</hi> when the <hi>Turk</hi> aſſaulted it: What wonder then was it if they ſo quickly over-ran that famous <hi>Empire,</hi> where <hi>vice</hi> and <hi>lazineſſe</hi> had generally infected all conditions of people.</p>
            <p>But now you ſee the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves have diviſions and diſſentions among them, their <hi>great Baſhaws</hi> and <hi>holy Muftees</hi> have their ſeverall factions and diſſentions; and whereas the <hi>poor Greeks</hi> by the reaſon of their hard uſage, begin now to be ſtarved into unity and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, they may ſeem to have changed their vices with the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170210:48"/> 
               <hi>Turks,</hi> who are now grown as factious and vitious as the other were before. Adde to all this that they are univerſally hated, and the neighbouring <hi>Princes</hi> raither <hi>wait</hi> a <hi>time,</hi> then <hi>want</hi> a <hi>will</hi> to be revenged on them for their many inſolencies. Put all theſe together, and tell me if it put not a cheerfull complexion on probability, that the <hi>Turkiſh tyranny</hi> having come to the mark of its own might, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt limits of its own great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, will dwindle and wither away by degrees. And aſſure your ſelfe, if once it come to be but <hi>ſtanding water,</hi> it will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be a <hi>low ebb</hi> with them.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170210:48"/>
            <p>Probably ſhe had proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed longer in her Oration, if not interrupted with the miſerable moanes and complaints of the <hi>Herbs</hi> and <hi>Flowers</hi> which the <hi>Boar</hi> was ready to devour, when preſently the <hi>Sage</hi> ſpake unto the <hi>Boar</hi> in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Liſten a little unto me, who ſhall make ſuch a motion whereof your ſelfe ſhall be the <hi>Judge</hi> (how much it tendeth to your advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage) and the deafeſt ears will liſten to their own intereſt.) I have no deſigne for my ſelfe (whoſe poſition here inviro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with with water, ſecureth
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170210:49"/> me from your anger) but I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed ſympathize with the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie of my friends and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which in the continent of the <hi>Garden</hi> are expoſed to your cruelty; what good will it do you to deſtroy ſo many <hi>Flowers</hi> and <hi>Herbs,</hi> which have no guſt or ſweetneſſe at all in them for your palate; follow my directions, and directly <hi>South-weſt</hi> as you ſtand, you ſhall find (going forward there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) a corner in the <hi>Garden,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vergrown with <hi>Hog-weed,</hi> (through the <hi>Gardeners</hi> negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence;) Oh what <hi>Lettice</hi> will be for your <hi>lipps;</hi> you will ſay that <hi>Via lactea</hi> (or the milkie way) is
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170210:49"/> truly there, ſo white, ſo ſweet, ſo plentifull a liquor is to be diſtilled out of the leaves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which hath gotten the name of <hi>Hog-weed,</hi> becauſe it is the principall <hi>Bill of fare</hi> whereon creatures of your kind make their common repaſt. The <hi>Boar</hi> ſenſible that <hi>Sage</hi> ſpake to the purpoſe, followed his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, and found the ſame true, when feeding himſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to ſurfet on thoſe delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dainties, he ſwelled ſo great, that in his return out of the <hi>Garden,</hi> the hole in the fence which gave him <hi>admittance,</hi> was too ſmall to afford him <hi>egreſſe</hi> out thereat; when the <hi>Gardiner</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:170210:50"/> coming in with a <hi>Guard</hi> of <hi>Dogs,</hi> ſo perſecuted this <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,</hi> that killed on the place, he made ſatisfaction for the wrong he had done, and for the terrour wherewith he had affrighted ſo many <hi>Innocents.</hi> I wiſh the <hi>Reader</hi> well <hi>feaſted</hi> with ſome of his <hi>Brawn</hi> well <hi>cooked,</hi> and ſo take our leave both of him and the <hi>Gardens.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170210:50"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
